Guide to the Milton White Papers ALBA.278
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Milton White Papers
1920-1946
1933-1939
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
White, Milton, 1917-
ALBA.278
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Milton White was born as Morris White in Cleveland in 1917 to Ephim "Hyman" White (born 1894 in Russia) and Tanya White (also known as Tania Martini). Within a few years, White was living in Brooklyn, where his parents were active in the Communist Party. The collection contains White's writings, incoming correspondence, and artifacts from the Spanish Civil War. A scrapbook and several notebooks belonging to his parents are also included.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Separated Materials
Fifteen photographs and one transparency were separated from the collection to form Series XXIX of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives: Small Photographs Collection (ALBA PHOTO 36).
Historical/Biographical Note
Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Milton White was born as Morris White in Cleveland in 1917 to Ephim "Hyman" White (born 1894 in Russia) and Tanya White (also known as Tania Martini). Within a few years, White was living in Brooklyn, where his parents were active in the Communist Party.
In 1937, White volunteered for service in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, which fought on the Republican side in the Spanish Civil War. He left for Spain on the Paris on March 27, 1937. While serving as a private, sometimes using the name Morris White, he was wounded several times. While in Spain, he wrote fictional stories, poems, plays, and songs about the war.
White returned home from Spain with a large contingent of veterans on the Ausonia on Dec 20, 1938. He joined the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) and was actively involved in VALB events for the next couple of years. A practiced musician, he often entertained attendees with his Spanish guitar.
During the Second World War, White served in the U. S. Army as a private. By the end of the war, he was serving in the Miami field office of the Military Intelligence Division.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains White's writings, incoming correspondence, and artifacts from the Spanish Civil War. A scrapbook and several notebooks belonging to his parents are also included.
Series I: Spanish Civil War, 1937-1939 contains artifacts, International Brigade documents, correspondence, and writings relating to White's service. The only outgoing correspondence is two brief notes to his parents. However, the incoming correspondence includes letters from his parents and friends, including two written by Spanish correspondents. White's fictional writings about the Spanish Civil War include stories, poems, plays, and songs (some of the latter in Spanish).
Series II: General Files, 1920-1946 consists largely of notes and notebooks kept by White's parents, mostly in Russian. There is also an identity certificate issued by the Russian Consul in New York to Ephim White in 1920. Finally, there is a small amount of material on Milton White's activities after his return from Spain.
Series III: Scrapbook is made up of pages from a scrapbook kept by White's parents during the time he was in Spain. Most of the material is in the form of newspaper clippings and flyers. It covers the subject of the Spanish Civil War, especially as it relates to White, as well as general leftist activities during this period.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series:
Series I: Spanish Civil War, 1937-1939
Series II: Subject Files, 1920-1946
Series III: Scrapbook, circa 1937-1939
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Provenance
The Milton White Papers were donated to the Tamiment Library by Judith and Jason Ross and Howard and Joanne White in December 2009.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, Jewish.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Poetry.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Songs and music.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Veterans.; Communism -- New York (State) -- New York; Jewish communists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; White, Milton, 1917-; White, Ephim "Hyman", 1894-; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion
- Series I: Spanish Civil War, 1937-1939
  - Artifacts from Spain (wallet and pins), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Ephim and Tanya White to Milton White, May and Aug 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Jack Sheldon to Milton White, Aug 1, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Milton White to Ephim and Tanya White, Aug 2, 1937, Dec 18, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Spanish Residents to Milton White (in Spanish), Jul 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: To Milton White on Return from Spain, Dec 20, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Unsigned Letter to Milton White (from Barcelona), Circa 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Brigade Documents about White, Apr 1937-Nov 1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Membership Books and Cards, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Pamphlet: Franco's 'Mein Kampf' (Spanish Information Bureau), Jan 1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Pamphlet: Galicia Martir estampas por Castelao, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Receipts from Spain, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Returning from Spain on the RMS Ausonia (Memorabilia), Dec 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Writings: Plays, Poems, and Songs, Circa 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1920-1946
  - Addresses and Business Cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence (incoming), Feb-Mar 1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Envelope Addressed to Milton White, Sep 11, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letter of Recommendation from Commanding Officer, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Notes in English and Russian (by Tanya White?), undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Notes in Russian, 1934, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Pamphlet: The Truth about Finland (Daily Worker), [1939] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - United States Army Uniform Patch, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - White, Ephim Identity Certificate Issued by Soviet Consul in New York City, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - White, Ephim Notebook: English and Russian (includes minutes of Communist Party Council 43 meetings), 1933 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - White, Ephim Notebook: Russian (I), undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - White, Ephim Notebook: Russian (II), undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - [White, Ephim?] Notebook: Russian (Milton White's name is on the cover), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Writings: Poems, circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Series III: Scrapbook, circa 1937-1939
  - Scrapbook Pages: Daily Worker Articles about the Return of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Veterans, including Milton White, Dec 20, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Scrapbook Pages: General, circa 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Scrapbook Pages: Milton White and the Spanish Civil War, circa 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Scrapbook Pages: Russian, circa 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 33)